# Oscar Barriga-Cabanillas

obarriga@worldbank.org | +1 (202) 701-3017 LinkedIn | obcabanillas.com

#### **Profile**

I am an economist specialized in poverty measurement, impact evaluation, and data science. My work combines household surveys and big data methods to study the impact of social programs. Most of my projects have involved a component of capacity building, training at the local and national government level, and result dissemination. My professional experience spans several developing countries, with projects in Colombia, Haiti, Mexico, and Paraguay.

I am proficient in several programming languages including Stata, Python, R, GIS, and Git. Besides data analysis, I developed several packages to estimate poverty, climate indicators, and applied machine learning algorithms to create small-area predictions of income and poverty using cellphone data. You can also check my academic CV in this link

#### Education

#### University of California, Davis

Davis, CA USA

Ph.D. in Agricultural & Resource Economics

2021

Dissertation: Essays on using cellphone data for development

Areas of specialization: Development Economics, Public Economics, Applied Econometrics

#### Universidad de Los Andes

Bogota, Colombia

Sept. 2012

M.A. and B.A. in Economics

## Work Experience

The World Bank

Washington DC, United States

Short Term Consultant

2021

• Study on the impacts of mobile network access on agricultural price dispersion in Africa

USAID

Davis, United States

Consultant 2018

- Impact evaluation of information dissemination campaign to promote mobile money adoption in Haiti
- Coordinated between the different areas of the cellphone provider to launch the project
- Team under supervision: 4 members

#### The World Bank

Washington DC, United States

Short Term Consultant

2016-2017

• Study on the effects of local market concentration on productivity in Mexico

#### The World Bank

Washington DC, United States

Junior Professional Associate

Sept. 2012 - Feb. 2015

- Core member of the Team for Statistical Development Group
- Analysis of social indicators across the region
- Designed tools to assure data quality and reproducibility of social indicators in the region
- Worked on designing an online platform to make data available to the public: LAC Equity Lab

## Colombia National Planning Department

Bogota, Colombia

Consultant

Apr. 2011 - Sept. 2012

- Developed a rural development plan for the western region
- Coordinated action plan with different entities at the national and local level

 $Bogota, Colombia \\ {\rm Apr.}\ 2010-{\rm Apr.}\ 2011$ 

Consultant

- Impact evaluation of national social programs aimed to reduce rural poverty
- Design and coordinate several data collection efforts

## Languages and Computer Skills

Statistical Packages: Python, R, Stata, IATEX, QGIS

Languages: Spanish (Native), English (Fluent), French (Read), Portuguese (Basic)

## Peer-reviewed Articles

"Fitting and interpreting correlated random coefficient (CRC) models using Stata." (with Tjernstrom, Michler and Michuda)

The Stata Journal, 18(1):159-173, 2018

"Inequality Stagnation in Latin America in the Aftermath of the Global Financial Crisis."

Review of Development Economics, 21: 157-181, 2017

"Is Uruguay More Resilient This Time? Distributional Impacts of a Crisis Similar to the 200102 Argentine Crisis." (With Lugo, Rodriguez-Castelanm Nielsen and Zanneti)

Journal of Banking and Financial Economics, 2 (4): 64-90, 2015

## **Book Chapters**

"Poverty and Shared Prosperity in Uruguay" (with Gindelsky, Lugo and Rodriguez-Castelan)
Shared Prosperity and Poverty Eradication in Latin America and the Caribbean. World Bank. Chapter 9

#### **Working Papers**

"Liquidity or Convenience? Heterogeneous Impacts of Mobile Airtime Loans on Communication Expenditure" Job Market Paper (with Lybbert)

"A Group Random Coefficient Approach to Modeling Heterogeneity in Technology Adoption." (with Tjernstrom, Ghanem, Lybbert, Michler and Michuda)

"The potential and limitations of big data in development economics: The use of cell phone data for the targeting and impact evaluation of a cash transfer program in Haiti" (with Blumenstock, Lybbert and Putman)

"Sharing resources in times of COVID: Lump Sum Transfers using mobile money in Haiti" (with Michuda)

"The Effects of Local Market Concentration and International Competition on Firm Productivity: Evidence from Mexico." (with Rodriguez-Castelan and Lopez-Calva) Revise & Resubmit in World Development

"Can information drive adoption of mobile money? A field experiment in Haiti"

"Improved Seed Adoption and Climate Change: Hybrid Maize in Ethiopia" (with Chiarella, Correa and Michuda)

## **Programming**

"PROSPERITY: A Stata module to compute the Shared Prosperity Convergence Index"

"Fitting and interpreting correlated random-coefficient models using Stata"

## Other Experience

## University of California, Davis

- Main Instructor: Development Economics (undergraduate)
- Teaching Assistant: Econometrics (graduate), Microeconomics

# Berkeley Initiative for Transparency in Social Sciences

• Code instructors in Stata and Python on several workshops in Berkeley (California) and Bogota (Colombia)

## Fellowships and Awards

Henry A. Jastro Graduate Research Award	2019
Research grant	
Digital Credit Observatory-Center for Effective Global Action (with Travis Lybbert)	2018
Grant to evaluate the welfare impacts of the introduction of Digital Credit in Haiti.	
Miguel Velez Fellowship	2017
Given annually to doctoral students judged to display scholarly promise	
Blum Family Foundation	2017
Research grant	
Berkeley Initiative for Transparency in the Social Sciences (BITSS)	2016
Research grant	

#### Conferences

- 2021: PacDev annual meeting, TSE Economic Seminar
- 2020: AEA annual meeting
- 2019: Bogota Experimental Economics Conference
- 2018: The World Bank Jobs and Development Conference, AAEA annual meeting
- 2017: AAEA annual meeting.